A Guide to the Affidavits for Ardent Spirits Collection, 1916-1917: SC 0091
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
1856-1897
1916-1917
Special Collections, James Madison University
Various
SC 0091
.33 cubic feet, 1 Hollinger box
The Affidavits for Ardent Spirits Collection, 1916-1917, consists of one Hollinger box of records documenting the inventory, sale, and transport of alcohol for medicinal purposes in Rockingham County. The collection references carrier companies such as Southern Express, Adams Express, and Wells Fargo, and local pharmacies and druggists such as Elkton Bottling Co., Aldhizer & Son Druggists, and Fletcher's Pharmacy.
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection is on deposit from the Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historical Society.
Historical Note
On March 10, 1916, the General Assembly of Virginia passed Chapter 146, an act foreshadowing the 18th Amendment of 1920. In this act, the General Assembly defined ardent spirits and went on to prohibit their manufacture, sale, transportation for sale, and general distribution. It further regulated the sale of alcohol for medicinal purposes by requiring those business who were allowed, by court license, to sell alcohol to file a monthly report, or inventory, of their alcohol on hand. This act was not written to prevent manufacture for consumption; it was intended to stimulate Virginia's temperance movement.
Chapter 146 was strengthened on March 19, 1918 with the passage of Chapter 388, which required that common carriers of ardent spirits be required to keep their records of quantities transported in an alphabetical file box. This was to include affidavits attesting to whom the alcohol was shipped, the amount and kind received, the date of delivery, and the cosignee. Both of these acts were repealed, however, with the passage of Chapter 403, section 504 (March 20, 1920), which required that the clerk of the circuit court of each county keep these affidavits in an alphabetically arranged book; therefore relieving the transportation companies of the duty.
Scope and Content
The Affidavits for Ardent Spirits Collection, 1916-1917, consists of one Hollinger box of records arranged in two series: Affidavits and General Documents.
Series 1, Affidavits, 1916-1917, documents the individual to whom the alcohol was shipped, the amount and kind received, the date of delivery, and the cosignee. Most affidavits are from the carrier companies Southern Express, Adams Express, and Wells Fargo. They are alphabetically arranged by county locale and further organized chronoglically. Due to their smaller size (4" x 6"), they are filed vertically and separated by tabs in lieu of folders. Oversize affidavits are foldered separately.
Series 2, General Documents, 1916-1917, consist of a single folder of monthly alcohol inventories from pharmacies and druggists such as Elkton Lithia Bottling Co., Aldhizer & Sons Druggists, and Fletcher's Pharmacy.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series:
1. Affidavits, 1916-1917
2. General Documents, 1916-1917
Bibliography
Acts and Joint Resolutions of the General Assembly of the State of Virginia, Sessions of 1916, 1918, 1920. Richmond: Davis Bottom, Superintendent of Public Printing, 1916, 1918, 1920, respectively. LAW: Laws, Statutes, Codes.
- Series 1: Affidavits, 1916-1917
  - Bridgewater, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Tab 1)
  - Broadway, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Tab 2)
  - Daphna, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Tab 3)
  - Dayton, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Tab 4)
  - Elkton, December 2, 1916-June 16, 1917 (Box 1, Tab 5)
  - Elkton, June 16, 1917-June 30, 1917 (Box 1, Tab 6)
  - Grottoes, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Tab 7)
  - Harrisonburg, December 19, 1916-June 6, 1917 (Box 1, Tab 8)
  - Harrisonburg, June 8, 1917-June 25, 1917 (Box 1, Tab 9)
  - Harrisonburg, June 26, 1917-June 30, 1917 (Box 1, Tab 10)
  - Island Ford, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Tab 11)
  - Keezletown, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Tab 12)
  - Linville, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Tab 13)
  - McGaheysville, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Tab 14)
  - Penn Laird, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Tab 15)
  - Rockingham (unspecified), 1916-1917 (Box 1, Tab 16)
  - Timberville, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Tab 17)
  - Oversize Affidavits, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Broadway and Harrisonburg (Box 1, Folder 1A)
    - Mt. Crawford (Box 1, Folder 1B)
    - Penn Laird (Box 1, Folder 1C)
    - Pleasant Valley (Box 1, Folder 1D)
    - Port Republic (Box 1, Folder 1E)
- Series 2: General Documents, 1916-1917
  - General Documents, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)